Hello, a very warm good morning to all
of you and welcome to an academy.
Welcome to today's the Hindu newspaper
analysis where we take a look at the
international edition of today's the
Hindu newspaper and look at the articles
relevant for the prelims and the mains
exam. At the same time, we also
understand the nuances of answer
writing. After all, that is very very
important in order to ace the civil
services examination. Now today in total
we are going to have a consideration of
10 different topics. Not many of them
are very relevant for the mains
examination. Most of them are relevant
for your prelims preparation for today's
newspaper. So the first article that we
are going to consider which has appeared
in the editorial page of the newspaper.
Socialism secularism are the spirit of
the constitution. We are going to
discuss what this article is about. Even
though it is a political article and
there is political connotation
associated with it that is political
parties and their role but then we are
going to keep the discussion bereft and
without any kind of political
inclination the discussion will be
restricted as per what is the
interpretation of the article with
relevance to the constitution. This is
relevant for your GS paper too. careful
curation. This is regarding the revision
of electoral roles which has been
observed and which has been ordered by
the election commission in the case of
the state of Bihar. Now there are
various concerns with this particular
revision what they are we are going to
talk about that relevant for your GS
paper too. Now there were certain other
articles in the editorial as well which
were not that important for the
examination. For example, in today's
editorial, there is an article
associated with parliamentary library
and how there is a need to use these
parliamentary libraries much more. Now,
that is an article that you can ignore.
Not very relevant for the mains
examination. And there is also a Q&A
kind of a uh long article about
imperialism of US. Again, nothing new
has been discussed there regarding what
we have been discussing for the past
couple of days. So, those articles have
been ignored. Now can the Supreme Court
halt an act passed by the state? Now
this is with regards to the contempt
proceedings which were filed uh in case
of the state of Chhattisgarh. Now what
that was and the provisions regarding
the constitutional arrangement we are
going to discuss relevant for your GS2.
Now some of the articles the remaining
of them are the ones we are going to
discuss for your prelims perspective.
Government clears indigenous defense
procurement worth rupees 1.05 lakh cr
post operation Sindur. Now that is a big
boost to defense production in India. A
new specy of tree has been found in the
region of Asam that is Garcinia Kusume.
Now what is that particular tree species
and what we can understand out of it?
Three Apache combat helicopters to
arrive in India by July 15 and the next
three in the next batch will be arriving
by the month of September. Endocrine
disruptors. So basically this is a long
article in the science section which
talks about that how plastic pollution
which was always regarded as a
theoretical concept now that plastic
pollution has got the endocrine
disrupting chemicals. So what they are,
what are these chemicals and what is
their impact on human health? That is
relevant again for the prelims. Rare
earth crunch a bigger disruptor to the
automobile sector as was previously
estimated that comes from CI. Now
services sector growth as per the PMI
the uh PMI index has hit a figure of 60
which is a 10-month high. Now drones for
reforestation have been used in the
region of Canada. So how is it that you
can use drones for the reforestation
program that is again something which
can be relevant for the prelims. So
these are the overall 10 different
articles that have been extracted from
the newspaper which are going to be
important for
having said that again to talk about
what we are going to offer this
particular weekend. So this particular
weekend that is 5th and 6th of July we
are coming up with the anac academy
summit where all the civil services
candidates they can attend the sessions
free of cost by enrolling in the link
provided in the description below and
why should you attend these sessions
first of all what is the requirement of
that the requirement from the very
basics let's suppose how to prepare the
or what are the resources to refer for
the subject of geography how to prepare
for your optional the various different
educators content creators, the
Olympians that we have, the
distinguished bureaucrats, the judges
and the part of the judiciary, they will
be a part of the panel which will help
you and guide you through the career
defining phase that all of us find
ourselves in. So do attend these
sessions on 5th and 6th of July and
enrich your overall experience and
knowledge of civil services examination,
the preparation and the life beyond
that. Now having said that we move on to
the first article of the day and that is
relevant that has appeared in the
editorial section and that is relevant
for your GS paper too. Now this is
socialism secularism are the spirit of
the constitution. So what is the context
of this article? Why has this article
been written? First of all let us
understand that the reason is simple.
Now recently we celebrate or we did not
celebrate rather but we observed 50
years since the imposition of emergency
one of the darkest chapters in modern
postindependent India and the
constitutional democracy that we enjoy
now that imposition of emergency that
raised several questions regarding
whether India could sustain
constitutional democracy for a longer
period of time or not and whether our
democratic setup is healthy or not. Now
after 50 years when there was a
remembrance a kind of observation of
those dark phases now thereby there were
statements issued by certain political
parties to get rid of all the various
changes brought about by the 42nd
amendment act to the constitution. Most
of you would be aware that in 1976 post
the impos imposition of emergency
emergency in case we are not aware was
imposed on 25th of June 1975
remained in force up until 1977.
In between that in 1976
42nd constitutional amendment act was
passed. Now obviously parliament was not
functioning the way it should when this
constitutional amendment was curated and
42nd constitutional amendment is also
referred to as the mini constitution in
reference to the number of changes which
were brought about in the constitution
with the help of this 42nd amendment.
Now many of these changes were further
reverted when the imposition or when the
emergency cease to exist and when the
Jantaa party government came in with the
help of 44th amendment and so on they
made or they made certain changes into
the constitution which reverted the
consequences of the 42nd amendment.
However, in popular imagination, in
media discussion and on the discourse on
social media, you will hear and
consistently come across the fact that
one of the key outcomes of the 42nd
amendment of the constitution, the 42nd
constitutional amendment
1976. There were many changes which were
brought about in the constitution with
the help of this particular amendment.
But the one which has been gaining
rounds quite frequently for a few years
now is the insertion of term secular and
socialist
in the preamble.
These terms were inserted in the
preamble. Now the argument which is made
by many of the political forces have
been that since these terms were in
inserted during the time of the
emergency that has changed the value of
the constitution and this has made these
terms to be an artificial addendum to
the constitution which was not
originally enshrined by the makers of
the constitution. Now that is where the
article is written in that context. The
article argues that look when you talk
about the terms socialism, secularism,
now these might have been inserted into
the constitution as a consequence of the
42nd amendment. But then the spirit of
secularism and socialism was always
present in the constitution be it in
part three of the constitution or part
four of the constitution. So the
constitutional character of our country
does embibe the aspect of secularism and
socialism and it is not only an outcome
of the 42nd amendment act 196
that is the entire premise of the
article. Now first of all without
focusing on the political leanings and
the political inclination of this
particular article. First of all let us
understand why is it that these words if
they are inserted into the constitution
why is it making such a large amount of
UN cry where different political parties
are issuing statement people from
different pressure groups are issuing
statements whether this word should be
there or not. Can a single word be that
very important in the constitution? The
answer is an emphatic yes. Every word,
every article, every particular letter
which is there in the constitution
carries its own meaning and carries its
weight. It shows the way in which the
constitution makers had envisioned a
future India to be and whether we are
keeping on the right track or not. The
constitution and each and every wording
of the constitution is an appropriate
barometer for the same. Now here it is
not merely a legal document. It embodies
the aspirations the ideals that a nation
state should have. And how did we come
across these aspirations, ideals,
everything which is included in the
constitution? One of the largest and the
lengthiest constitution across the
world, everything was thought upon. And
that was a resultant, a culmination of
our lived experience, our civilizational
experience, our civilizational values,
our freedom struggle. Now all of them
all of these particular struggles they
had taught us a lot of things and those
were put into
so even when let's suppose there is an a
case in front of the Supreme Court and
the judges of the Supreme Court take a
particular decision in any direction
made towards or against. Now they take a
look at the constitution and they
interpret each and every wordings of the
constitution. That is why every
insertion, every omission and every
elimination becomes very.
Now here let us understand that the
article argues that even if you ignore
these words secular and socialist from
the preamble still the constitution had
enough amount of ideas regarding
socialism and regarding secularism.
So how so first of all what do we
understand by the term socialism? This
is a term that you have been hearing
about time and time again. What is this
idea of social now? Its definition has
changed over the decades. The very root
cause and the idea of socialism that is
something which emerged in Europe in the
1900s and that is when it was emerging
as a political idea. But in the 20th
century, in the early part of 20th
century, very soon this idea of
socialism was juxtaposed with an idea of
communist state and communism became a
rallying cry and the very ideals of
socialism that started taking a
backseat. But when we talk about
socialism, what is the dictionary
definition of?
So if you take a look at the dictionary
definition
any of the various egalitarian
which achieve equality economic or
political theories or movements
advocating collective or governmental
ownership and administration of the
means of production and distribution of
goods.
Now the idea is that any large scale
production of goods, production
mechanism for that matter that should
not be individually owned that should be
owned by the society. So that the
decisions which are taken the decisions
which are made those decisions are taken
by the participants in the method of
production rather than certain
capitalists who are sitting at the top
of the food chain. Now this idea started
gaining traction because in the 1900s
and the early 20th century the larger
world and the global awakening was
against inequality.
Mind you, we still are in the midst of
a very severe inequality across the
globe. But at that point of time, people
started thinking that how to remove
inequality.
Karl Marx had famously said that the
world is divided into the halves and the
have nots. The halves who have all the
property rights etc who have all the
money they can take decisions for a
larger or for the larger public and the
larger public has to keep on following
that. That is where Mark said that this
leads to the vicious cycle of poverty
that the working class is always trapped
in. Now that inequality and the
persistence of inequality basically
enabled the global community to think
about a future where the society would
own the methods of production and that
was the thought process even behind
insertion of the terms.
But then this term socialist is it
something which is only included or is
only included in the preamble and talked
about only in the preamble? The answer
is no. When you take a look at it, the
preamble other than the term socialist
also mentions justice, social, economic
and pol. Now you cannot achieve social,
economic and political justice in any
particular society without having the
ideals of equality and removal of
inequal inequality and the factors of
production should never be concentrated
in a singular hand. Now the article
argues that if you read part three and
part four of the constitution together
then that also indicates that Indian
constitution always had the basic DNA of
when we talk about let's suppose part
three of the Indian constitution that is
the part of fundamental rights. Now
within that when we talk let's suppose
about article 14
what is it equality article 14 deals
with equality the importance of equality
now equality again cannot exist in a
society where only few have all the
resources under their control. When you
talk about article 15, article 16,
now both 15 and 16 they talk about the
requirement of removal ofination.
Any discrimination on the basis of
religion, race, cast, sex that should
not happen. The region that should not
happen. That is what the article 15 and
16 they talk about. So equality and
removal of discrimination will be
fulfilled when when you have a society
consisting of equals. And when do you
have a society consisting of equal? When
everybody has a joint ownership.
Ownership in deciding their own fate in
their own destiny. And along with that
if you read articles of associated with
part four with articles of part four so
particularly let's suppose article 38
41 even 43 for that matter. All of these
articles that you read about now these
are the part of directive principles of
state policy
DPS
isn't it? Now these DPS they direct the
state about how the state should behave.
So this is at a level whereby the state
should not discriminate. Every person
should have equality at an individual
level. But how the state should behave
also indicates that the framers of the
constitution they thought and they waste
the Indian state and the Indian
governance method to be that of equality
and social justice. Now just a brief and
a uh customary reading of these
particular articles particularly 38 and
39 because I I'm sure uh you guys would
have read all these articles in much
greater detail. So a brief customary
reading. If you take a look at article
38, what is article 38 about? Secure a
social order for the promotion of
welfare of the people. Right now the
state shall strive to promote the
welfare of the people. How? By securing
and protecting as effectively as
possible a social order in which justice
social economic and political shall
inform all the institutions or basically
form all the institutions of the
national life. So even the institutions
should have this socialist character
right equality. Now strive to minimize
the inequalities in income.
endeavor to eliminate inequalities in
status, facilities and opportunity not
only amongst individuals but amongst
group of people. Right? Again insisting
on equality and removal of any kind of
certain concentration of wealth,
concentration of power. But this is much
more clearly defined if we progress to
article 39. And when we talk about
article 39, so what does it talk about?
So state shall direct its policy towards
securing that citizens, men and women
have the right to an adequate means of
livelihood. That the ownership, this is
important, ownership and control of the
material resources of the community.
Ownership and control of all the
material resources. The tangible
resources that a community has are so
distributed as best to subserve the
larger common good. When the factors of
production are controlled only by a few
then that leads to discrimination that
leads to concentration inequality. But
when it is owned by a larger public and
a larger mass it is to affect a larger
Right? Operation of economic system does
not result in the concentration of
wealth and means of production for the
common detriment. So that tells you
about the general socialistic
characteristic character that the
constitution had much before the 42nd
amendment to the constitution was even
talked about. Right? So this basically
leads us to the conclusion that the
entire argument about socialism was well
enshrined into the much early. Now what
about secularism?
Now secularism is not the case in
particularly in our case when we talk
about secularism in Indian context. It
is different for example when we talk
about secularism in the French context
with respect to the other constitution.
So secularism in Indian context what
does it mean? It talks about it is not
about by the way religious neutrality.
It is about treating all the religions
together
right or at the same level. So positive
assurance that state will not have any
kind of discriminatory approach towards
any religion. Right. and protection of
minority rights are a very important DNA
and a very important factor in that
entire fabric of Indian Indian
secularism. Now the argument and the
allegation which is often times muddled
towards uh uh the 42nd uh amendment or
otherwise as well is that this
secularism was and secular word was
inserted during the time of the
emergency and in our case we have a very
different treatment of secularism
altogether.
The answer to that is always that the
constitution makers, the framers, they
always thought about the secular
characteristic that Indian state should
have. That was a learning from our own
freedom struggle. Article 25 to article
30 of the constitution distinctly talk
about the secular nature that the Indian
state should have and the protection of
minority rights. Particularly article
2930 they talk about the protection of
the minority rights and the word secular
it is not as if the word secular was
only inserted into the preamble. If you
take a look at article 25 part two the
word secular is used there as well. So
thereby the aspect of secularism again
if even if we take a look at the
articles from 14 to 7 all of them they
talk about equality and lack of
discrimination based on religion. So
they also talk about a kind of a
positive aspect of secularism where all
the religions are treated equal no
discrimination right. So even without
the insertion of the term secularism in
the preamble Indian constitution had the
DNA of secularism the argument which can
be made force uh forcefully for that
matter. The original text of the
preamble even without insertion of the
word secular. What was the original
text? Liberty of thought, expression,
belief, faith and worship.
Now can you have this enshrined in the
preamble if the idea is never to have a
secular state? If the idea is never to
protect the minority rights, the answer
is no. So that is why the aspect of the
gamble talking about secularism even
prior to the ins term is the key point.
Now, secularism overall enshrined and
further reinforced with various
different articles. Article 14 to 16,
article 25 to 28, right? Freedom of
religion and conscience, freedom of
practice, profess and propagate the
religion, freedom from religious
instruction in a certain uh educational
institutions. Then article 29 and 30
cultural and educational rights of the
minority community all of them they
reinforce the concept of secularism in
the constitution. Now here what is the
importance of these terms?
The importance overall is that these are
the guiding principle to the welfare
nature of the governance
and also one of the guiding light when
it comes to constitutional decisions
made by the courts of justice. For
example, all these included in part
three and part four of the constitution,
particularly part three, they form the
very important basic principles of the
constitution. And in the famous 1973
case of Ananda Bharti case, the Supreme
Court had opined that the basic
structure cannot be violated either by
legislative action or any other action
otherwise administrative,
and so on. So that basically tells us
that each and every wording here that is
working as a lighthouse to show us a
path into the future. And this is not an
absolute uh random word that we are
talking about. These are the learnings
which we have gained from our lived
experience, our civilizational
experience and also the much fraught
freedom struggle that we struggled with.
Right? So this is basically the
importance of these particular.
Okay, I hope that is understood. Now the
practice question, I hope we are able to
answer this. The ideas of socialism and
secularism have been included in the
constitution post 42nd constitutional
amendment 19th amendment.
Now here what is the ask of the
question? Is the question asking you or
is the examiner trying to ask you here
to explain 42nd constitutional
amendment? No. The demand of the
question is very simple. You have to
argue and you have to comment on the
statement that the idea of secularism
and socialism came into the constitution
only after 42nd constit of amendment
act. whether that is true or not. Okay.
So you have to analyze that. So how do
you write the answer for this? What do
you write in the intro for this? The
intro here you can say basically again
there are various ways and templates in
which you can introduce. One way to
introduce is by talking about what is
meaning of what is the meaning of
socialism and secularism. That can also
be a method to introduce your answer.
Another method to introduce the answer
would be starting with the 42nd
constitutional amendment 1976
brought substantial changes to the
constitution including the insertion of
the terms secular and social in the
preamble of the constitution. So in the
intro set the context.
Okay. I hope every day when we are
discussing these questions and sample
questions talking about how to curate
the answers I hope at least a few of us
are able to write the answer and are
able to practice. Okay, this is not just
for a mere and sheer entertainment that
you are simply watching it and thinking
you will embibe some outcome out of it.
Right? So please do practice it. This is
for your benefit that I'm going and we
are going into this much depth of answer
writing on a daily basis. Okay. Now here
let the context for
insertion in
of terms in the preamble.
Okay, that is important.
After that
that's it. That should be your
introduction. Nothing more.
After that what do you do in the body
portion
because it is about comment right. So in
the body portion you start talking about
that these terms they are not mere
addendums but basically something that
the framers of the Indian constitution
had always thought about. So that is
where you start writing about evidences
indicating that the constitutional
provisions other than the preamble also
include the characteristic and the DNA
of socialism and secularism. Now please
keep one thing in mind in case in your
introduction you have not used the uh
used or you have not clearly mentioned
what is the meaning of secularism and
what is the meaning of socialism. Do
that in the body. In case your
introduction itself has talked about the
meaning of socialism and secularism,
fair enough. Set the context in the
body. Right? So whichever approach you
are taking for introduction, the body
should compensate for the other one. So
here set the tone for what is the
meaning not a very detailed. Okay brief
because it is a 10 marker. So in a
single sentence or two sentences at max
right after that the evidences for both
of them separately if possible.
Okay now then the conclusion.
In the conclusion what do you write?
Conclusion, you talk about the
importance
maintenance of secular fabric and
socialist ideas in welfareism. They not
only herald a brighter future but also
ensure that as a society, as a
civilization, we learn how to move ahead
and how to respect the diversity as well
as ensure unity of the community that we
live in. like that you can frame your
own wordings. The conclusion should
always talk about the importance and the
kind of a wayfall. Okay, I hope that is
understood. Now what should be the
conclusion when the tone of the question
is neutral always forward-looking and
positive? Always chir that is what I
gave you the example of. Yeah. Can I
mention some fundamental right articles?
That is what you have to mention under
the evidences. You have to mention the
articles. Articles both in part three as
well as part four.
Okay. Both of them have to be mentioned
here. Right. Now to write the answer.
These kind of questions are asked by
UPSC quite freely.
Now is it correct to say if we frame in
our answer by considering what is right
and what is wrong?
I'm unable to understand your question
Rahul. But if you are asking that should
you take a stand that secularism is
wrong or right or socialism is wrong or
right. Now if you are at the verge of
that dilemma in your mind that you want
to issue a judgment that no secularism
is not needed or social whatever these
kind of personal opinions that you have
write it in a piece of paper fold that
piece of paper put that in the cupboard
lock the cupboard and throw the keys as
long as you are appearing for the civil
services examination these personal
thoughts and dilemmas that you have need
not be put into the paper you are
appearing to be an administrator Right
now as a future administrator for the
government or uh for the uh governance
and larger welfare of the public these
are the ideas that you should swear by
these are the ideas you should talk
about that yes why they are important in
case I'm not able to convince you in our
discussion of half an hour then write
these in a piece of paper and throw that
paper away but in answer copy you need
to support these ideas okay Manisha if
possible Well, why not? Now after that
we come to the other article that is
careful curation.
Now for the past few days there has been
a lot of news during the rounds with
regards to the revision of electoral
roles which has been initiated by the
election commission for the forthcoming
Bihar elections.
Now what do we mean by electoral roles?
By the way, when we talk about electoral
roles,
what is the meaning of that? Now
electoral roles is an official document
consisting of all the voters or
including all the voters which are who
are supposed to uh put or cast their
vote in any particular electoral
role of a region. Now across the world
the electoral rules keep on being
updated. They are updated quite free.
What is the requirement of updation of
electoral rules? Why do we need to
update the electoral?
Because let's suppose in a broader
concept we will understand and minutia
and minute details you can extract on
your own if you understand the larger
aspect. Let's suppose you talk about a
larger region your state any state that
you belong from. Now in that particular
district a let's suppose the electoral
roles have been prepared today this
thing has been done.
Now after 2 years let's suppose a family
moves out another family moves in and
they start living in few people have
died newer people have come of age isn't
it? They have gained the age of 18 years
and above they become eligible to vote.
Now if let's suppose this electoral role
is not updated in the next 10 years then
what does it mean? It means that within
that official list of voters, I will
still have the names who are long gone,
the names of those who basically have
died, have moved out and will not
include the names of those people who
have started living in that region for a
long period of time or even those names
of those per vote. The revision of
electoral roles is the absolute
necessity for the reflection of the
opinion and the will of the voter. Now
the will and the opinion of the voter
cannot be expressed unless and until the
electoral roles are updated. Now the
electoral roles are updated by the
election commission of India under the
provisions provided to it by article 324
of the constitution and also as a
consequence of the registration of
electors rule reer 1960.
So based upon these two, article 324,
the representations of people act 1950
and the registration of electoral roles
rules 19 uh or 1960.
These are the three norms by which the
election commission keeps on updating
these electoral rules. Now here why is
it such a bigger issue and why is it
such a greater amount of conflict when
it comes to the political parties in the
state of Bihar. Already you have various
political thinkers like Yogendra Yadav
who is who wrote a a detailed uh article
in the Indian Express citing it as a
part of a larger conspiracy in order to
manipulate the voting patterns across
the country to have bogus voters put in
and the genuine voters to be eliminated.
So the opposition parties they are up in
arms and the election commission is
adamant that we need to carry out this
revision. But before we go into the
details of what this revision is. So
here first of all the types of revision.
Now the types of revision basically
here they are driven by rule 25
of
1960.
Rear 1960. What is 1960? Registration of
electors rule 1960. Now as per this
there are three types of revision.
Summary revision
where a broader
revision is done not going into the
absolute details and a broader
revalidation of the voting list and the
electoral role is done. Right? Then you
have intensive revision
where all the uh suggested or all the
voters who have not been there in the
previous electoral role now if they want
to be included they have to show the
proof of residence the proof of birth
etc. And that is very intensive
exercise. And then you have partly
intensive,
partly intensive and partly summary.
Right
now in general what do you observe that
almost every year or before every
election this summary revision of
electoral rules is done and there is not
much of a debate noise which is created
by that. But this time before the Bihar
election intensive revision of the
electoral rules is cited by the election
commission and that is what has created
lot of noise around it. Now why is there
a need basically or why is there a talk
of this intensive summary intensive
revision of the ele? The reason for that
first of all
when was the last revision of the
electoral roles carried out in Bihar?
That is important. If you think about it
now that last revision was not carried
out the last decade or in the last two
decades also the last revision was
carried out in detail revision was
carried out in 2003.
Now think about it
there have been 22 years which have
passed.
Now many new voters would have many new
voters would have been born after that
for that matter. Now their name if not
included in the summary revision would
have not been there in the electoral
roles at all. Many people have migrated
permanently out of the state. Now Bihar
is a state consisting of a large group
of migrant population. Now in our
previous news analysis we had discussed
one article which talked about capturing
the migrant population's vote being one
of the important criteria for a state
like Bihar where you have daily wage
earners and other people also migrating
out of the state both on a permanent as
well as a semi-permanent basis. So for
that you need to understand what is the
electoral role out there. Now hereby
understand this when we talk about the
need for revision this is also keeping
in mind migrant population
migration pattern
right and also the case of many people
who have passed away new elect new
eligible voters and so on. But there is
a larger concern which is raised.
The concern is that this intensive
revision of electoral roles if you are
carrying that out the process which has
been chartered out by the election
commission it talks about that look if
your name was not there in the previous
electoral roles if you want your name to
be there if you are a new eligible voter
you have just reached uh 18 years of age
and so on you have to furnish the
documents right the documents need to be
furnished which documents are we talking
birth certificate
and residential proof. These are the
documents which indicate that you are
actually a resident of that state. Now
the finalization of this document
verification is got to be done by end
July.
End July.
Now the fear which is present and the
concern which is there which is very
logical as well is that let's suppose
those migrant population who are not
living in Bihar right now but who would
want to vote and who are permanent
residents of Bihar now they won't be
able to furnish documents before the
officers the booth level officers uh
prior to July end so their name will be
stuck off for the from the electoral
roles for a longer period of time isn't
it so what about the mig migrants,
migrants who are unable to publish the
document.
Now another important issue which has
been raised for the past few days. Now
it is not written in the article but it
is important to discuss that as well.
Now I told you that Yogendra Yadav had
come up with a detailed article talking
that this is a part of a larger
conspiracy. While that is an idea which
can be debated whether it is a larger
conspiracy or not. But there was an
important point which was raised in that
article. The point being that the onus
of being a voter of a particular region
has now shifted from the state the voter
by this particular action. What is the
meaning of the statement? Let us
simplify the statement. Whether I am a
voter in Bangaluru or Karnataka. Now
earlier the state would carry out the
verification process and the state would
keep on updating that. The argument is
by carrying out this exercise there is a
large scale shift of responsibility for
the voter from the state the eligible
voter. So it is now the responsibility
of the eligible voter to prove to the
election commission that yes I am a
registered voter of this particular
region. Which means what which whose
implication will be what? Many eligible
voters who are not able to show their
documents in time, who are not able to
furnish those occu documents in time,
they will be discarded from the
electoral
and at the same time the burden of proof
becomes so very heavy that this will
further reduce voter particip.
So understand this the burden of proof
is going to
whether for right or for wrong.
Now that is a matter for separate
discussion. But the reality as a
consequence of this action is burden of
proof shifts the voter
and when the burden of proof shifts to
the voter
voter participation will be further
less.
Isn't it?
Now for an electoral democracy,
voter participation is an important yard
stick to determine whether the
democratic exercise is being carried out
successfully or not. So this is not a
good example for that matter. Now what
is the way forward in this? All of us
here who are present, all of us will
agree that revision of electoral rules
is a must. I I'm sure nobody will deny
that fact that revision of electoral
rules is a must. Now when you revise
those electoral rules, document
submission is also a must. Otherwise
there will be many of the fake names in
the uh electoral rest but at the same
time the burden of proof is also an
issue. So what is the way forward in
this?
always when the election commission has
been knowing that let's suppose the
state of Bihar goes to election at the
end of 2025
why couldn't this exercise been carried
out let's suppose since past one and a
half years after all the voters from
that particular state will have a much
greater time available to them in order
to furnish the document in case they
don't have those documents they can make
those documents or they can get those
documents ment isn't it? So there should
be a larger time window which shall be
should be as at the same time the very
important parameter when it comes to
electoral roles and the revision etc is
the requirement and the importance of
transparency
regularly on the on the kind of a portal
on the kind of a district list the voter
roles and the electoral roles can be and
should be published. It is available to
the political parties but then that
should be available to the larger public
much prior as well. Now it is done
through the apps but in those areas
already election commission has got the
app where you can track whether you are
a voter in a particular constituency or
not. But then in areas where you have
still got the digital divide where that
digital literacy is not that high in
those cases there can be public
declaration of these role that these
names are there in the voter list and in
case you don't find your name you can
come and contact us. So that
transparency is a must because without
that transparency the very faith in the
electoral democracy and the
parliamentary system of election that
erod and that is where we get a kind of
a perfect consequence of misgovernance
right so I hope this particular issue is
understood beyond this article as well
and into a greater depth okay now the
issue of the migrants to be dealt
And that is where capturing the migrant
population. So what do you need to do?
Greater time allocation,
greater time allocation,
one of the issues.
Other than that,
greater consultation
with the parties in question,
greater amount of consultation with the
uh ind with the individuals, political
groups, pressure groups, etc. and
transparency.
These are a must.
Okay. Now after this we come to the
practice question. Discuss the
importance of revision of electoral
rules in a parliamentary democracy. A 10
marker answer needs to be written for
this. So how do you write the answer in
the introduction the intro you have to
talk about what do you mean by electoral
role? What is it?
Then in the body you start by talking
about who does it? The election
commission of India under which
provisions. So basically article 324
then representations of people act 1950
and revision of electoral rules 1960.
Now the types of revision also you
mention summary revision, intensive
revision, part summary, part intensive
revision. Then talk about that when we
talk about the need for the electoral
revision of the electorals roles. Why is
there a need updation regular updation
to capture the migrant population to
capture the new voters and to capture or
also to eliminate the redundant voters
which are there or the redundant names
which are not eligible for voting
anymore who have moved to other states
uh who have passed away all of that. the
importance to capture the public opinion
the best possible accuracy as possible.
Right? Like that you can write the
answer. Okay. Now after this we move on
to the next article. Census data is
useless in order to get the migrant
data. Yes, census data does not capture
the migrant details. It is carried out
on a decadal basis. So that is why the
census data is not very appropriate. In
fact, the first time a detailed migrant
uh uh aspect or the enumeration was
captured by the economic survey in 2016
2017. If you look at that economic
survey and if you take a look at the
source of that data, Arvindra
Subramanium would uh would be the CEA
chief economic adviser at that point of
time. Now, where did they fish the data
to get the amount or the number of
migrants? They actually used a very
innovative idea to take a look at the
railway reservations, the railway
tickets and with the help of that they
could gauge an idea about the internal
migration which was going on and that is
when they got to a realization that in
fact millions of people they tend to
right domestically right so that is why
census details are not very uh apt.
Now uh I have a question by Nad uh when
fresh batch of geography optional will
start for 2026 batch. As of now there is
no intention to launch a fresh batch for
geography optional for 2026. This is a
call made by the management. In case you
want to take a look at the English
optional for geography, you can take a
look at the uh recordings which are
available. But no new fresh batch is
being launched as of now. Okay. Now
after this we come to the other article.
Can the Supreme Court halt an act passed
by the parliament? Now hereby when we
talk about the entire article the
context of it. So the context of it is
set by a contempt plea which was filed
in the Supreme Court. There was a
contempt uh plea which was filed whereby
the PIL talked about that Supreme Court
should actually punish the Chhattisgarh
government or actually hold the
Chhattisgarh government for contempt in
action. Why? Owing to the fact that
Supreme Court in 2011 had made a
statement had made a judgment in the
famous case of Nandi Sundar and others
versus the state of Chhattisgarh. Now
what was this case about? Now those of
us who are unaware now problem or the
problem of left-wing extremism has
prevailed in the region particularly
across the red corridor for a long
period of time. Now thereby many of the
states like Jharkand, Chhattisgarh what
they started to do they started
utilizing and arming the local tribal
population with certain small arms and
so on and basically they were made to
fight against the Knoxel attacks as
well. Now the tribals and the villagers
they often times found themselves in the
crosshair of both the kn as well as a
security force because the knuckles they
would be angry that these villagers they
have targeted us and if they would not
pick up the arms the security forces
would look them with a suspicious eye.
So that is where the entire movement
which was named as Salva Judum
in the region. Now that Salva Judum was
seen to be extrajudiciary, right? And
that is something which was seen to be
uh illegal. That is when you had a case
which was filed in the court that please
ensure that this is not carried out.
this process is not carried out. In the
judgment which was issued by the Supreme
Court, certain fierce observations were
made. Now, Supreme Court said that how
can you do this? How can you arm
untrained individuals and how can you
put them into the battlefield? Now, they
have not signed up for this and there is
no provision for this. Now, this is
violative of article 14 and 21. Right?
Now they were referred to as a special
police officers, SPOS's.
So how could you do this? So it turned
the entire thing as illegal and banned
groupings like the Salvaj. It also
directed the Union government that you
should also not make any rule right and
you should not start or you should not
fund this recruitment of special police
officer.
Now after this immediately after the
Supreme Court judgment, Chhattisgarh
government made a new law whereby it
changed the legislative aspect of it. It
provided a legislative power to itself
whereby it created Chhattisgarh
Auxiliary Armed Police Forces Act
2011.
So think about it. Judiciary issues a
particular judgment where it says that
special police officers taludum arming
of tribals is illegal. What does
Chhattisgarh government do? Create a new
law whereby it makes it legal as per the
law as per the state legislature. Now it
basically creates certain mandated
recruitment conditions. For example,
auxiliary police force to aid security
forces. They will not be the frontline
forces. They will aid the security
force. And what did the Supreme Court
had? What was the judgment and the
observation of the Supreme Court?
Supreme Court had said that look they
are poorly trained and inadequately
paid. At the same time you have to
recall all the firearms that you have
issued. Poorly trained. So what does
that legislation do? Legislation said
that they would not take frontline
combat roles first of all and at least 6
months of training would be done only
after that after fulling fulfilling the
required conditions would someone be.
So it is like bypassing the judicial
observation.
Now that is where you had recently in
the recent days a fresh petition which
was filed that the Supreme Court should
hold the Chhattisgarh government
accountable for contempt action. Supreme
Court in its observation has said that
look we cannot hold the state government
for contempt based upon whether it has
framed a legislation or not. And that is
where it cited the previous case that is
Indian aluminium company and the state
of Kerala. Under this particular case as
well, the Supreme Court in its
observation had focused on particularly
the doctrine of separation of powers
of separation of powers.
Judiciary has got its own role and
legislature has got its own rule. In the
case of Indian aluminium company versus
the state of Kerala, again the case was
the same. If you analyze the details of
the case, Supreme Court had made an
observation. Now after that you
basically had the state government
forming a new legislation to bypass the
judicial observation. Now there also the
Supreme Court had opined that this
doctrine of separation of powers needs
to be respected so that there is no
judicial overreach or no overreach of
other arms of governance.
So that is where the Supreme Court holds
its stance that state legislatures they
have got the plenary powers to enact
laws unless that law is unconsil
you can frame a law right. Passing a new
law even on similar lines cannot be
contempt of court unless it directly
violates an express directive of the
Supreme Court.
Supreme Court has directly said that
let's suppose in this particular
territory you cannot deploy the police
forces and you deploy the that is
violation but Supreme Court had talked
about special police officer and here
Chhattisgarh government is doing what
creating a separate branch with the help
of training uh the training of arms and
then a proper recruitment cycle. So it
is not an expressed directive which is
being violated but a separate mechanism
a channel an official channel so to say
being created. So thereby it is not
illegal. Courts must respect the
doctrine of separation of powers between
the judiciary and the executive. So that
is the crux and the nutshell of this
particular article whereby the case
example has been taken for the case in
Chhattisgarh that is Nandini Sundar and
others versus the state of Chhattisgarh.
So keep that in mind and the aspect of
when a contempt proceeding cannot be
initiated against the state legislature.
Okay. Now certain articles which have
been in news relevant for the province.
First of all, government clears
indigenous defense procurement worth 1.0
like 05 lakh cr. Now this is post
operation synindur. Now this is a big
boost to India's defense acquisition and
most importantly India's defense
production, indigenous defense
production. All of them have been
ordered under the by category. By
category of india
indigenously
IDM as it is referred to indigenously
designed
and
developed
and manufactured.
Okay, under this category.
So that is also referred to as IDM.
Okay, this was the revision of the
procurement policy in defense production
which was done around 2016 in order to
bolster the self-reliance in defense.
Now this large scale procurement is in
which category? That is important to
note not only for those who are defense
enthusiasts but even for your prelims
purpose. One is your QR SAMs. What are
QR SAMs?
Quick reaction surfaceto-air missiles.
The one which is indicated in the image.
Now this is usually uh employed or
deployed for air defense against drones
against aircraft. Now this is your final
tier of defense. After this you
generally tend to deploy guns. But in
terms of missiles this is one of the
final layers. It has got a shorter range
very shorter range of around 10 to 15 to
20 km in certain cases 30 km. Beyond
that you have the MR SAMs that is where
the category of uh the Barak missiles
they come in the case of MR SAMs and
then you have the LR SAMs. So like that
you have the various different ranges.
Now this is a short range QR sams are
short range for air defense. So this has
been ordered to bolster the air defense.
Then you have the EW suites.
What are EW suites?
Electronic warfare. Electronic measures
and counter measures. For example,
during operation Synindur, you would
have observed the statement by the DGMOS
where they said that we used various
different static and kinetic actions in
order to prevent the Pakistani drones
from reaching their targets. Isn't it
static and kinetic action? Kinetic
action means you fire a missile against
a drone, the drone is destroyed. But
what is that static action? You
basically electronically jam the drone
and the electronics of it or you spoof
it. You in a way hack it or you send so
much amount of electronic signature
noises that it tends to get misled
rather than hitting the target here. The
drone is misled or the missile is misled
somewhere else. So that is your
electronic warfare right. So EW suites
also what has been ordered amongst the
other categories stored uh vehicles etc.
Another interesting part is the
autonomous submersible vehicles.
Autonomous submersible vehicles they can
be used in general to carry out shallow
water attacks against an enemy navy and
the kind of complete disarmament of the
naval force. This is generally used by
elite uh special forces across the world
for stealth activity. Now this has also
been ordered. Now one of the important
aspects is that your elite commandos
will have this especially the marine
commandos or the marcos. The other
important aspect to note is that we have
developed the capability to manufacture
autonomous submersible vehicles. Till
now this capability used to exist in
certain countries like the US, China,
France, Germany was developing it. UK is
said to have developed it but India also
has got a reliable development chain and
a link to it. So that makes it
important. Now then another article new
Garcinia species found in Asam named
after botonist's mother. So we are
talking about Garcenia Kusum. Now you
don't need to know the name of the
botonist or the name of botonist's
mother. You just need to focus on the
specy in question. So this garcenia
kusume now it is basically it was it is
an asamese tree variety where in asam it
is also known as toura. Now here it is
known for its edible fruits in general.
Now it grows alongside
bamboo the trees of shisham also. Now
erretia in all these areas it will tend
to grow. So moist regions in some amount
of moisture that is where it will grow.
Edible fruits medicinal properties
anti-obesity and anti-diabetary
effect as well. So that is the aspect of
this particular specy in new now then
after that three Apache combat
helicopters to arrive in India by July
15. Now the defense minister of India
has had a kind of a dialogue with his US
counterpart where many statements were
made. First of all, India's right to
self-defense, preemptive strikes, all of
that were made. But certain important
discussions on defense was also done
regarding the supply of the Apache
helicopters. Apache is a combat
helicopter. Now Indian army had ordered
these Apache helicopters and placed that
order with the US. But then the delivery
of these Apache helicopters have been
very staggered and for a long period of
time this has impacted our offensive
capability. Now mind you these Apache
helicopters they are deployed by the
strike core the one which is meant for
the offensive action. These will be
placed in the region of Jelmme right at
the bordering region. Now they have a
state-of-the-art technology with helmet
helmet mounted display whereby the arms
and the uh targeting system for example
if the pilot looks in a certain
direction automatically the target
shifts in that direction. So that is one
of the capable state-of-the-art
technology that these Apaches have. Also
they have a low radar cross-section. So
they have some of the stealth
characteristic which is required by
these helicopters and they can flow at a
terrain heging height very low height
which can evade detection by radars as
well. At the same time in this
particular discussion another important
point was raised and that was regarding
the engines to be supplied. Now I hope
we are aware that India is manufacturing
the light combat aircraft LCA
particularly the LCA Mark1 that delivery
has been pending for a long period of
time from the side of HAL and the
argument is that this tends to utilize
the GE 404 engine General Electric's 404
engine and G is not supplying that
engine due to which our rollout of LCA
Mark1 has been dealing
So that is what the discussion was held
and at the end of the discussion it was
understood it was agreed upon that the
engine supply is one of the key areas
that both of them have to focus on for
the quicker roll out of LCA Mark1. Okay.
Now after that a detailed article has
appeared in the science section of
today's newspaper that is endocrine
disruptors in plastic waste a new public
health care health threat. So basically
the context of the article is that look
India is the largest plastic poller in
the world not amongst the largest but
actually the largest whereby we end up
producing close to around 9.3
in terms of the tonnage etc. 9.3 tons in
terms of the plastic waste almost on a
daily bas
out of this only close to around 5.3
they are so it is 9.3 million tons
rather I apologize
tons per year
out of that 5.3 million tons
per year
they are burnt incinerated
Rest of them
almost 4 million tons
they are out there in the environment.
They get broken down into smaller size.
That is what we refer to as
microplastics. These microplastics get
embedded in our skin and that is when
they cause hormonal issues. They have
been found to cause hormonal issues and
also issues in terms of reproductive
health of humans. more particularly
pronounced in regions like India and
China. So here these are known as EDC or
endocrine disrupting chemicals. What are
these EDC?
So basically biophenol A and overall BPS
they are used in water bottles, food
containers and thermal paper. Also you
have phalates that is DHP and also PFAS
also known as forever chemicals. All of
these they get inserted into our skin
and into our digestive system
eventually. The outcome of it is that
they mimic or block the natural hormones
that is estrogen, testosterone, thyroid
hormones and cortisol which is leading
to in many cases uh the case of Mumbai
has been cited where the experiment was
done, sampling was done in majority of
the samples across major Indian cities.
the early reaching of puberty due to
testosterone excess or difficulty in
terms of the reproductive cycles due to
the issue in the follicles and also the
semen samples containing microplastics
in China and India. So the influence is
very significant. Now they interfere
with receptor binding, disrupt gene
expression in rep reproductive organs
and induce oxidative stress and in so
what are those chemicals? What are EDCs
and what is their impact? Now rare earth
crunch a bigger issue for auto firms
than expected is a statement was issued
by confederation of Indian industry CI.
Now CI basically uh in its briefing
talked about that the fact that I hope
we are aware that the Chinese they have
put a kind of an export ban on the rare
earth elements based magnets. Now many
of the magnets which are devised they
use these rare earth elements. Now as a
consequence multiple different sectors
of production across the world
particularly in manufacturing they have
been impacted. countries from the US to
India they have been impacted by the
supply shortage. Now this also brings to
attention that we need to have a kind of
a robust supply chain uh characteristic
or a logistic method where we are not
only dependent on countries like China
because China has done it previously as
well. Now automobile sector in our
country is going to be impacted where
they are expected to carry out
production cuts. Now when you cut down
the production, what does it lead to? It
leads to unemployment.
Why are you carrying out production
cuts? Because you don't have the
minerals, the critical minerals. You
don't have those magnets. Now that will
lead to unemployment. And that
unemployment will further to a loss of
demand in the economy because people
don't have enough money to spend because
they don't have a job. And as a
consequence of that loss of demand,
lower production again,
right? And that lower production again
fuels the cycle of unemployment. All of
this because of lower production
due to supply chain issue.
Okay. So that is the cycle that the
Indian automobile sector is staring at.
Now services sector growth hits 10-month
high as the demand surges. So basically
purchasing managers index or PMI this
purchasing managers index is a kind of a
survey mechanism where newer orders the
price pressures the newer employment
everything is carried out amongst the
industry and basically for the month
which has passed there is an idea for
the manufacturing sector and also the
services sector which is carried out.
Now if this PMI number is around 50 that
means there is no growth no contraction.
If it is less than 50 that means the
sector is contracting. If it is greater
than 50 that means there is an
expansion. Now PMI for the services
sector have for the month of June has
indicated number of 60 which is very
very high. This is based on newer demand
in the services sector and that is
fueled by the domestic demand which is a
good news because when services sector
faces a newer demand its ability to
generate employment is manifold. It is a
job multiplier where let's suppose $1
that is put in the services sector can
yield for example tourism can yield $6
in the allied activities as well. So
like that it can have a job multiplier
effect as well. Okay. Now coming to the
last article that is Canada uses drones
for reforestation of wildfire
hit forests. So the region of Canada has
been experiencing wildfires quite
frequently in the past decade and a half
or not if you even if you take a shorter
time window almost for the past 5 years
wildfire events have been very common.
Now generally when you have a wildfire
if you leave that area naturally there
will be regrowth of the forest. But then
the problem is that if every year this
wildfire keeps on destroying your
forests then the time to regrow will be
so high that in the long run you will
always face a decline in the forest
health decline in the forest area. So
what what many regions have started to
do including Canada they are using the
drones to spread the seeds. Now the
seeds basically are embedded in a
capsule.
Okay. They use AI in order to map the
physiography, water requirement, natural
climate of a region in order to
understand the suitability of a
particular seed in a region. Now what do
they do? They basically use the capsules
and in that capsule they bring the seeds
the some of the fungal species as well
to ensure greater rate of germination
and the seeds that they are using are
for black spruces and jack pines. Now
overall the seeds are protected in the
capsule. So the capsule consists of some
moisture
seeds
and fungi
to ensure faster germination.
Okay. So that is being done. It can also
be incorporated in countries like India.
Okay. So that brings us to the end of
the discussion for the day. I hope the
discussion was meaningful and has added
some of the content. Now if you have
liked the discussion put that in the
comment section and don't forget to
click on the like, share and the
subscribe button. Tomorrow we will meet
in the evening for the discussion of the
places in news for the month of May or
the for the month of June 2025. Do take
a look at the space of uh the anac
academy is English channel and thereby
ensure your revision for the places in
news so that it is carried out in a
comprehensive manner. tomorrow and day
after tomorrow there is also that summit
where you can interact with the various
educators firsthand and gain experience.
So till that point of time do you take
care goodbye. Thank you.